Look out pardners, there's a new mouse in town!
An American Tail: Fievel Goes West is a animation,
family, western film directed by Simon Wells.
Some time after the Mousekewitz's have settled in America, they find that
they are still having problems with the threat of cats.
That makes them eager to try another home out in the west, where
they are promised that mice and cats live in peace.
Unfortunately, the one making this claim is an oily con artist named Cat R.
Waul who is intent on his own sinister plan.
Fievel Mousekewitz (voice), played by Phillip Glasser.
Wylie Burp (voice), played by James Stewart.
Mama Mousekewitz (voice), played by Erica Yohn.
Tanya Mousekewitz (voice), played by Cathy Cavadini.
Papa Mousekewitz (voice), played by Nehemiah Persoff.
Tiger (voice), played by Dom DeLuise.
An American Tail: Fievel Goes West (also known as An American Tail 2: Fievel Goes West or An American Tail II) is a 1991 American animated Western musical comedy adventure film directed by Phil Nibbelink and
Simon Wells (in their feature directorial debuts), with producer Steven Spielberg for Amblin Entertainment and animated by his Amblimation animation studio and released by Universal Pictures.
A sequel to 1986's An American Tail, the film follows the story of the
Mousekewitzes, a family of Russian-Jewish mice who emigrate to the Wild West.
In it, Fievel is separated from his family as the train approaches the American Old West; the
film chronicles him and Sheriff Wylie Burp teaching Tiger how to act like a dog.
Fievel Goes West was the first production for the short-lived Amblimation, a studio
Spielberg set up to keep the animators of Who Framed Roger Rabbit (1988) working.
It is also the only Amblimation film to use cel animation, the last in the
series to do so, and the last to be released in theaters.
While the animation medium was transitioning to computers in the late 1980s and early 1990s, Spielberg wanted almost all of
the animation of Fievel Goes West to be hand-drawn, describing animation as "an arts-and-crafts business".
He also wanted the animation to have a "live-action" feel.
Phillip Glasser, Dom DeLuise, Nehemiah Persoff, and Erica Yohn reprise
their roles from the first film for Fievel Goes West.
Tanya's original voice actor, Amy Green, was replaced by Cathy Cavadini, and new characters were
voiced by John Cleese, Amy Irving, Jon Lovitz, and James Stewart in his final film role.
James Horner returned as a composer and wrote the film's song "Dreams
to Dream", which garnered a Golden Globe nomination.
Premiering at the Kennedy Center on November 17, 1991, An American Tail:
Fievel Goes West began its American theatrical run on November 22.
This was the same day Walt Disney Pictures' Beauty and the Beast (1991) was distributed, making
it the third instance of two animated films being released on the same date.
Fievel Goes West was promoted with a wide array of tie-ins
and started in the top ten at the box office.
The film grossed $22 million in the United States
against a budget of $16 million.
Some film journalists and executives attributed this to
having to compete with the Disney film.
Upon its release, Fievel Goes West received mixed reviews from critics: while its animation, score, and voice
performances were praised, most criticisms targeted its story, pacing, and lack of character development.
However, it found success when it came to home video sales, quickly reaching the top of the video charts when released on tape in March 1992; at
the time, the film held the record for shortest theater-to-home-video transfer, and it has since gained a large cult following.
In addition to garnering more home media releases, television airings, and video game adaptations later on, the film has made
numerous 2010s retrospective best-of lists from online publications, especially best Netflix-available Western films.
Fievel Goes West was followed by a short-lived CBS series named Fievel's American Tails and two direct-to-video films: An
American Tail: The Treasure of Manhattan Island (1998) and An American Tail: The Mystery of the Night Monster (1999).
The film explores themes of sheriff, indian territory, mouse, villain, sequel.
The tone is lighthearted.